<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Plotly | Alex Mathew]]></title>
  <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/plotly/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-17T00:05:54+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Mathew]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexmathew003@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/03/the-tnt-journey-part-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T04:56:57+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/03/the-tnt-journey-part-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new approach. Better results.</p>

<p>Here, I&rsquo;ll share the team I generated based on the stats I used, and my insights on the numbers involved.</p>

<p>The grand curtain call to this series.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>These were the teams generated -</p>

<p>ALL STAR XI :
Shane Watson, Hashim Amla, Virat Kohli, Kumar Sangakkara, AB de Villiers, MS Dhoni, Shahid Afridi, James Tredwell, Dale Steyn, Saeed Ajmal, James Anderson</p>

<p>BENCH - James Faulkner, Andre Russell, Rangana Herath, Jos Buttler</p>

<p>INDIA XI :
Virender Sehwag, Shikhar Dhawan, Virat Kohli, Rohit Sharma, Suresh Raina, MS Dhoni, Ravindra Jadeja, R Ashwin, Bhuvaneshwar Kumar, Amit Mishra, Mohammed Shami</p>

<p>BENCH - Gautam Gambhir, Manoj Tiwary, Vinay Kumar, Umesh Yadav</p>

<p>I made a bubble chart comparing batsmen&rsquo;s ERA and milestone values, and multiple bar charts to compare bowler stats across various over groups. (Thank you, <a href="http://plot.ly">Plotly</a>)</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/16.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/23.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/24.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/25.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/27.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>


<p>Insights about the teams and the related stats :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>AB, MSD and Kohli are ridiculously valuable to the team. They put up big scores and they do it at an excellent strike rate. People like Sanga and Rohit Sharma are the kind of people who&rsquo;d play an average-paced innings, but put up a score to set the tone of the innings. Shahid Afridi is a classic pinch hitter (any cricket fan can vouch for that). Very few milestone innings, but he adds a lot of value in terms of his scoring rate.</p></li>
<li><p>Cricket nowadays seems to revolve around the quality of the wicketkeeper-batsman in the team. When I considered the overall batting performance ratings to pick the batsman for the team, there were 4 keepers in the top 10 - MSD, Sanga, Jos Buttler and Quinton de Kock. Granted Buttler and de Kock are relatively new and haven&rsquo;t played a lot, but the fact that they start off immediately as valuable batsman shows the value of a good batsman who can perform well behind the wickets.</p></li>
<li><p>It turns out Amit Mishra has been India&rsquo;s most valuable bowler. In terms of pure wicket taking ability, he really stands out above the crowd of Bhuvi-Shami-Ishant-Umesh Yadav and the others.</p></li>
<li><p>Any Indian cricket fan would already know this - Indian bowlers are pathetic in the death overs. After Zaheer and Ajit Agarkar at his peak, India has almost never had a good death-over bowler. This fact is very obvious from these graphs - Shami and Bhuvi get tonked in the death. Ishant Sharma and Umesh Yadav - who didn&rsquo;t feature in the main XI - don&rsquo;t fare too well here either.</p></li>
<li><p>Dale Steyn is the MVP among bowlers. By quite a margin, actually. James Tredwell has had good performances, but the problem is the limited number of matches he has played. James Anderson is a classic strike bowler - a brilliant opening spell marked by an excellent economy rate and some wickets, and a death-over spell where runs flow but a lot of wickets fall.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>You can obviously argue with a lot of these numbers. Your argument will be justified because there are flaws in the approach taken to get these teams.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It doesn&rsquo;t consider form or the venue where they played. This would change a lot, especially with the Indian XI. Viru wouldn&rsquo;t be in the running for the spot at the top, and I wouldn&rsquo;t have had to deal with Praveen Kumar and Irfan Pathan almost making the cut. Also, Amit Mishra&rsquo;s value may have dropped if you considered overseas performances. An intuitive look at the team will give some more credit to new players who are putting up good performances - Ajinkya Rahane and Ambati Rayudu in place of Sehwag and Rohit Sharma.</p></li>
<li><p>It doesn&rsquo;t considering fielding/wicketkeeping performances. Picking the primary keeper for this team was solely on the basis of their batting contribution. This issue came up because there was no way to know the total number of matches they had played - I discussed that situation in <a href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3/">Part 3</a> of this series. It just assumes that everyone in the modern cricketing world is a good fielder, and they wouldn&rsquo;t even be playing if they were poor fielders.</p></li>
<li><p>There are definite limitations on the stats I have considered. You could argue there is some metric that would show that someone else is better than someone on these teams. I really need to learn more about statistics.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So that&rsquo;s it from me. This has been an amazing 3 weeks with this problem. Somehow, being awake felt worthwhile.</p>

<p>Thank you LatentView.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-tnt-journey-part-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T00:32:23+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-tnt-journey-part-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With all the work looking at the player side of stuff, I didn&rsquo;t spend too much time on the venue-based side of the problem. So I decided to get that done. What can sides expect in Australia and New Zealand ?</p>

<p><a href="http://plot.ly">Plotly</a> continues to impress with its usefulness.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I couldn&rsquo;t come up with any really useful statistical measure to judge the performance in a particular venue, so I decided to go with three basic numbers - runs per 50 overs, wickets per 50 overs and boundaries per 50 overs - and put them in a 3D scatter plot (which turned out to be pretty easy with Plotly).</p>

<p>It was back to MongoDB&rsquo;s aggregation framework to put this together. I went with the same workflow that I had with aggregating player data - write the aggregation commands, use a Python script to create a new collection with all the data.</p>

<p>There were 89 unique venues in the given dataset. However, we couldn&rsquo;t go with the entire set because 30 of those venues hosted only one match, and one match is definitely not enough to observe a pattern. For example, there was only one match played at the Chinnaswamy Stadium and batsmen went all berzerk during that match - that also included Rohit Sharma&rsquo;s 209. But not all matches at the Chinnaswamy produce 600+ run spectacles. So there should be a minimum number of matches that a venue should have hosted if it has to be considered. Going with a minimum of 3 matches, we have a list of 40 venues (which notably exclude MAC, Wankhede and Eden Gardens).</p>

<p>Working with these 40 venues, we set up a collection which contains the three stats that we are considering for each venue. Now it&rsquo;s just a matter of setting up the 3D scatter plot on Plotly. Since we are grouping by country, we need the country that the venue is located in. This was the annoyingly hard part - manually finding the country.</p>

<p>Now with some basic statistics on the data I have, and the generated 3D scatter plots, we can make some conclusions.</p>

<p>The scatter plot with all the countries which have venues in the dataset.</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/10.embed" width="800" height="800"></iframe>


<p>Specifically with Australia and New Zealand.</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/11.embed" width="800" height="800"></iframe>


<p>Across the 9 venues in Australia and New Zealand, the mean 50 over score increases by more than 10 to reach a score of 247, while the mean wickets/50overs remains almost the same - around 7.5. So expect many lower-order pinch hitters to make cameos. With 300+ scores becoming commonplace in ODI cricket, expect this mean 50 over score to increase over the course of the World Cup. Expect the average of 25 boundaries/50overs only from mediocre teams - if a team really has to make a mark, they&rsquo;ll have to step up that number. This World Cup is a funny mix because Australia is known for its longer boundaries, while New Zealand is known for its shorter boundaries. Batting fests are extremely possible in NZ, while Australia will host more balanced battles.</p>

<p>More insights soon.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll also continue working on finding a good way to build the team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/29/the-tnt-journey-part-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T09:17:35+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/29/the-tnt-journey-part-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you have exams and an interesting problem that you have to complete in a few days, it&rsquo;s not too cool to go down with a fever. These next couple of days are going to be a blaze with all the work. I need to get this done with.</p>

<p>Before picking the teams, I needed a way to visually represent the data I had so far. I needed to have the graphs look beautiful, and also easy to generate.</p>

<p>Enter <a href="https://plot.ly">Plotly</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I think of it more as, the GitHub of Graphs.</p>

<p>I heard about Plotly during PyCon India 2014. I found it really interesting and decided to use it for any interesting project I had to work on (also because I put a Plotly sticker on my laptop, so I had to use it because I donated laptop real estate to it). Just as I was looking for ideas of things to work on, I came across TNT, so I decided that it might be a good time to start using Plotly.</p>

<p>It was so much easier than I thought.</p>

<p>I decided to use the <a href="https://plot.ly/python">Plotly Python API</a> for generating some visual representations of the data. The documentation is very extensive, and the examples given are usually more than enough to get you going. The best part is how easy it is to collaborate and work on the graphs across languages/tools - when you have the link to your graph, all you have to do is add a .py or .r or .js or .m to work with the graph in Python, R, Javascript or Matlab. The link with .png gives the graph as an image, and .html gives an iframe that embeds the graph in a web page. How cool is that !</p>

<p>I decided to go with using iframes mainly because I wouldn&rsquo;t have to edit the webpage every time I edited the graph. It would be really useful when I worked on my data often.</p>

<p>So I went ahead and built histograms for each of the 7 batting/bowling statistics that I mentioned in the <a href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3/">previous post</a>.</p>

<p>Starting off with the batting stats.</p>

<ul>
<li>Runs per wicket</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/1.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Runs per 100 balls</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/2.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Pinch hitting rate</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/3.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<p>The bowling stats.</p>

<ul>
<li>Overs to concede 100 runs</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/4.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Wickets per 10 overs</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/5.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Overs to concede 10 boundaries</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/6.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Overs to concede an extra</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/7.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<p>Now, this is useful to notice how I can&rsquo;t use the entire player dataset to generate my team, because it would end up skewed in favour of players who rarely played. A player who has bowled only one over in the given timeframe, and conceded just 1 run along with taking a wicket will have statistics like 100 overs to concede 100 runs and 10 wickets per 10 overs - which is obviously messed up. So I need to set a minimum number of innings that a player should have batted or bowled in, if the player has to be considered for the team. I&rsquo;m setting that number at 23 - I&rsquo;ll see how it turns out and make changes if I have to.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll continue using Plotly to represent other statistics of the generated team. And that is what I&rsquo;ll have to start working on now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
