<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tnt | Periphrastic Prolixity]]></title>
  <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/tnt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-16T00:09:08+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Mathew]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexmathew003@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cause I'm TNT, I'm Dynamite]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/cause-im-tnt/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T23:33:31+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/cause-im-tnt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Yes, I just made an AC/DC reference)</p>

<p>First off, huge shout out to LatentView Analytics. Thank you for the job placement offer ! It&rsquo;s given me so much peace of mind, and in turn, freedom to experiment with new stuff.</p>

<p>About a week back, I heard about LatentView&rsquo;s new event for final and pre-final years - &ldquo;The Number Thing&rdquo;. Or, TNT. Perfect experimentation ground.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>All the problems were interesting. It was just a matter of picking the right one.</p>

<p>Cricket stat analysis.
Crime pattern analysis.
Text analysis.</p>

<p>One sports analytics question, and I was sold. That was my choice. Cricket Craze.</p>

<p>I knew it would be a lot of fun. I also expected it to be challenging. What I didn&rsquo;t expect was a 175373-row dataset. I knew this would be a whole new challenge for me. This was the biggest dataset I&rsquo;ve had to work with so far. I had to get new tools in my arsenal to tackle this. This was going to be a crazy ride.</p>

<p>I decided to blog about what my approach to this problem. Think of it as documentation. Over the next few posts, I&rsquo;ll break down my approach - from the initial steps, all the way down to the final result (hopefully!).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this and think there&rsquo;s a better way than the approach I&rsquo;ve taken, do give your suggestions ! Also, suggest resources to get started with them. You can write to me at alexmathew003[at]gmail[dot]com</p>

<p>Check out the &ldquo;TNT&rdquo; category on the blog to read the posts. I&rsquo;ll make regular updates as I make progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
