<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Alex Mathew]]></title>
  <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-17T00:05:54+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Mathew]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexmathew003@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Have to Talk About Scrapple]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2016/06/15/i-have-to-talk-about-scrapple/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-15T15:45:07+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2016/06/15/i-have-to-talk-about-scrapple</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>*One and a half years after my last blog post*</em></p>

<p>I maintain <a href="https://github.com/AlexMathew/scrapple">a project on Github</a>, and I can&rsquo;t shut up about it. I won&rsquo;t deny that I talk about it a lot, and that&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m proud of it. But I still don&rsquo;t have a proper way of explaining it to people. I think I have to start writing about what it can do.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I started working on Scrapple in late 2014 (which was about the time I wrote <a href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/12/09/what-i-learned-from-my-first-hackathon/">my last blog post before this</a>). It was an idea that was running on my mind for a while - an itch that I wanted to scratch. The snowball effect struck, and in a few months, Scrapple was sort of a big deal on Github (for a day) and I felt this unusual sense of responsibility that I had to explain to people what exactly it was that I was trying to achieve. I have met people who could relate to the problem and have given me some great advice and suggestions. To the other people who could not relate to it, I have tried explaining the idea of Scrapple.</p>

<p>And I have failed. Quite miserably.</p>

<p>I have tried to maintain an extensive documentation of the entire code base. But in terms of people trying to use Scrapple, this does not particularly help. These people want to know how Scrapple can be useful to them, how to get started with using it, and the various options they have at their disposal. <a href="http://scrapple.readthedocs.io/en/latest/#experimentation-results">The couple of examples that I have added to the Scrapple documentation</a> were definitely not enough for all this. I had to do more.</p>

<p>Add this need with <a href="https://medium.com/@alxmth03/winner-winner-chicken-dinner-ec11112170ab#.p0kb90a9m">my decision to try to start writing</a> and the fact that I have no real way to maintain my blog so far, and I think I have a solution. Write about web scraping in general, and how Scrapple fits in.</p>

<p>I might manage to get my blog alive, get a clearer picture of what I am trying to achieve with Scrapple, and have an overall better understanding of maintaining a project and getting people involved in it. And have fun doing it.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know how often I&rsquo;ll manage to write, or what exactly I will be writing. I&rsquo;ll let this take shape in time.</p>

<p>Hopefully, it works out well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Learned From My First Hackathon]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/12/09/what-i-learned-from-my-first-hackathon/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-09T18:54:53+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/12/09/what-i-learned-from-my-first-hackathon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I finally got to do something I&rsquo;ve always wanted to. I took part in a hackathon.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://koding.com/Hackathon">Koding hackathon</a> was a 48-hour online hackathon, which happened over the first weekend of December 2014 (not going for specific dates, because timezones). For me, it was a great choice for a first hackathon because it helped eliminate the biggest problem that stopped me from taking part in a hackathon so far - getting to the venue. This was in the middle of my holidays, and I could work from home. Everything felt right. I managed to complete my working web app, &ldquo;<a href="http://github.com/AlexMathew/g33k">G33K</a>&rdquo;, in the 48 hours (I did screw up big time, though). It was a great sense of accomplishment knowing that I had the most productive 48 hours I&rsquo;ve had in a long time. And over that weekend, I learned a lot.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what I learned from my first hackathon.</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li><strong>Get a team</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Do <strong>NOT</strong> go for a hackathon solo, no matter how good you are. It&rsquo;s always better to have people to share the load with. I didn&rsquo;t expect to get shortlisted to the hackathon, so I didn&rsquo;t talk to anyone about teaming up with them. Once I got the email from Koding that I was in, I scrambled to find a teammate. I asked a few of my friends, but none of them were free for the weekend, and that&rsquo;s when I decided to go solo for the hackathon. It was fun to try to take the whole thing alone, but after a while it gets to you. You need a team to share the work and to share the load of the pressure.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Find a comfortable position to work</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>I could barely move my neck after the 48 hours, and I&rsquo;m not even 21. This is more than just about a hackathon - this is something I should have in mind considering I may be working long hours very often. I need to find the most comfortable and physically ideal position for working, and incorporate it.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Maintain your todo list</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Lack of sleep is not an ideal situation to be in while working, but it&rsquo;s something you&rsquo;re forced into during a hackathon. So when you&rsquo;re sleep-deprived, it&rsquo;s not too easy to remember what you have to do or how you planned to do them. Have a notepad or use post-it notes to keep track of everything you need to get done. This is a great way to avoid forgetting to put in some feature that you originally planned to.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Be comfortable with your stack</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>There are two ways you can decide a stack for your hack - use something you are familiar with, or experiment with something you&rsquo;ve always wanted to try out. A hackathon is a great platform to learn new skills or to cement expertise in existing ones. But either way, it&rsquo;s good to have a basic working idea of everything you will be using, so you don&rsquo;t waste time learning from scratch during the hackathon.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Make sure you don&rsquo;t make noob mistakes</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>Sleep deprivation does bad things to you. Very bad things. In a sudden moment of idiocy, you could end up making stupid mistakes that you notice too late. There&rsquo;s not a lot you can do to &ldquo;avoid&rdquo; this - just hope you keep your sanity through the entire duration of the hackathon.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Be sure about your deployment options</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>The PaaS industry gives you so many options. <a href="http://heroku.com">Heroku</a> is my personal favourite. You could also go for extremely popular options, like Google App Engine. But in some cases, you will have to improvise - case in point, the Koding Hackathon. The hackathon required participants to host their apps on Koding VMs. That meant I had to think about Apache or Nginx and all that stuff, in the last 2 hours of the hackathon. It was especially hard because I never had to worry about such stuff before. I managed to get it done (barely!), but it made me realize that it is necessary to have some basic knowledge about such sysadmin stuff.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Get help as soon as possible</strong></li>
</ul>


<p>During a hackathon, you definitely do not have time to stay stuck on a problem for too long. Get help as soon as possible. Ask people around, check StackOverflow or other answers pages and check the docs/FAQs again. If it&rsquo;s a problem with a particular service, message their support team or send them a tweet. Good services have an active service/support team that will respond immediately. Get your problem sorted out quickly and get back to work !</p>

<hr>


<p>Getting through till the second round of judging is a really huge achievement, given how much I had to scramble to put this together. I know where I messed up, so I know quite well what I have to fix. I plan to continue working on G33K - fix up my mistakes, add new features and deploy it.</p>

<p>I learned a lot from this hackathon, and it also gave me an awesome side-project to work on.</p>

<p><strong>Coming soon : #G33K by Team #TheY2KProblem</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/03/the-tnt-journey-part-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T04:56:57+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/03/the-tnt-journey-part-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A new approach. Better results.</p>

<p>Here, I&rsquo;ll share the team I generated based on the stats I used, and my insights on the numbers involved.</p>

<p>The grand curtain call to this series.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>These were the teams generated -</p>

<p>ALL STAR XI :
Shane Watson, Hashim Amla, Virat Kohli, Kumar Sangakkara, AB de Villiers, MS Dhoni, Shahid Afridi, James Tredwell, Dale Steyn, Saeed Ajmal, James Anderson</p>

<p>BENCH - James Faulkner, Andre Russell, Rangana Herath, Jos Buttler</p>

<p>INDIA XI :
Virender Sehwag, Shikhar Dhawan, Virat Kohli, Rohit Sharma, Suresh Raina, MS Dhoni, Ravindra Jadeja, R Ashwin, Bhuvaneshwar Kumar, Amit Mishra, Mohammed Shami</p>

<p>BENCH - Gautam Gambhir, Manoj Tiwary, Vinay Kumar, Umesh Yadav</p>

<p>I made a bubble chart comparing batsmen&rsquo;s ERA and milestone values, and multiple bar charts to compare bowler stats across various over groups. (Thank you, <a href="http://plot.ly">Plotly</a>)</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/16.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/23.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/24.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/25.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>




<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/27.embed" width="750" height="500"></iframe>


<p>Insights about the teams and the related stats :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>AB, MSD and Kohli are ridiculously valuable to the team. They put up big scores and they do it at an excellent strike rate. People like Sanga and Rohit Sharma are the kind of people who&rsquo;d play an average-paced innings, but put up a score to set the tone of the innings. Shahid Afridi is a classic pinch hitter (any cricket fan can vouch for that). Very few milestone innings, but he adds a lot of value in terms of his scoring rate.</p></li>
<li><p>Cricket nowadays seems to revolve around the quality of the wicketkeeper-batsman in the team. When I considered the overall batting performance ratings to pick the batsman for the team, there were 4 keepers in the top 10 - MSD, Sanga, Jos Buttler and Quinton de Kock. Granted Buttler and de Kock are relatively new and haven&rsquo;t played a lot, but the fact that they start off immediately as valuable batsman shows the value of a good batsman who can perform well behind the wickets.</p></li>
<li><p>It turns out Amit Mishra has been India&rsquo;s most valuable bowler. In terms of pure wicket taking ability, he really stands out above the crowd of Bhuvi-Shami-Ishant-Umesh Yadav and the others.</p></li>
<li><p>Any Indian cricket fan would already know this - Indian bowlers are pathetic in the death overs. After Zaheer and Ajit Agarkar at his peak, India has almost never had a good death-over bowler. This fact is very obvious from these graphs - Shami and Bhuvi get tonked in the death. Ishant Sharma and Umesh Yadav - who didn&rsquo;t feature in the main XI - don&rsquo;t fare too well here either.</p></li>
<li><p>Dale Steyn is the MVP among bowlers. By quite a margin, actually. James Tredwell has had good performances, but the problem is the limited number of matches he has played. James Anderson is a classic strike bowler - a brilliant opening spell marked by an excellent economy rate and some wickets, and a death-over spell where runs flow but a lot of wickets fall.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>You can obviously argue with a lot of these numbers. Your argument will be justified because there are flaws in the approach taken to get these teams.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>It doesn&rsquo;t consider form or the venue where they played. This would change a lot, especially with the Indian XI. Viru wouldn&rsquo;t be in the running for the spot at the top, and I wouldn&rsquo;t have had to deal with Praveen Kumar and Irfan Pathan almost making the cut. Also, Amit Mishra&rsquo;s value may have dropped if you considered overseas performances. An intuitive look at the team will give some more credit to new players who are putting up good performances - Ajinkya Rahane and Ambati Rayudu in place of Sehwag and Rohit Sharma.</p></li>
<li><p>It doesn&rsquo;t considering fielding/wicketkeeping performances. Picking the primary keeper for this team was solely on the basis of their batting contribution. This issue came up because there was no way to know the total number of matches they had played - I discussed that situation in <a href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3/">Part 3</a> of this series. It just assumes that everyone in the modern cricketing world is a good fielder, and they wouldn&rsquo;t even be playing if they were poor fielders.</p></li>
<li><p>There are definite limitations on the stats I have considered. You could argue there is some metric that would show that someone else is better than someone on these teams. I really need to learn more about statistics.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So that&rsquo;s it from me. This has been an amazing 3 weeks with this problem. Somehow, being awake felt worthwhile.</p>

<p>Thank you LatentView.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/01/the-tnt-journey-part-6/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-01T21:06:27+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/11/01/the-tnt-journey-part-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>31 October 2014. 7 PM. Struggling because I don&rsquo;t have an eye for design and I didn&rsquo;t know what to do about the infographic. Struggling because I wasn&rsquo;t satisfied with the result I got with this. And that was when rescue arrived.</p>

<p>Deadline extension.</p>

<p>I have never been this happy about a deadline extension. These two extra days give me a lot of time to fix what I&rsquo;d done. And to fix the unsatisfactory results I had, I had one choice - to change the logic I was using.</p>

<p>I had to start from scratch.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The two days gave me a lot of time to fix the stats I was considering for the selection. Yeah, I had a semester practical exam at the end of those two days. But still, priorities.</p>

<p>So first, there were two things that happened before the initial deadline that made me unhappy with my results.</p>

<ul>
<li>I couldn&rsquo;t get the genetic algorithm thing working. I had to manually pick the best players for each category.</li>
<li>I had to settle on using just the basic stats I had to pick the teams.</li>
</ul>


<p>I ended up with a decent All Star team - Watson, Amla, Kohli, AB, George Bailey, Kane Williamson, MSD, Andre Russell, Steyn, Rangana Herath and Anderson. But the Indian team I got had Praveen Kumar in it. Not Bhuvaneshwar Kumar, not anybody else who&rsquo;s ever bowled for India. I got a guy who&rsquo;s been &ldquo;out of action&rdquo; for quite a while. I knew this thing was messed up. But I didn&rsquo;t have a lot of time to fix it, so I went ahead with it.</p>

<p>So when I heard about the deadline extension, I knew had time to right these wrongs. I got to reading articles on Cricinfo about suggestions for new statistics (I can&rsquo;t believe I didn&rsquo;t do that before). So with help from a few friends who reviewed the teams I was generating and suggested new factors to consider (thank you Pranav, Lakshmi and Arjun), I picked a bunch of new factors to consider.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Mike Hussey&rsquo;s &ldquo;Magic Number&rdquo;: I read about this number that Mike Hussey suggested for comparing T20 batsmen. A good T20 batsman would have (Average + Strike Rate) > 160. This means, a batsman scores an average of 40 runs at a rate 120 runs in 100 balls is as valuable as a batsmen who scores an average of 20 at 140. I didn&rsquo;t try to judge ODI batsmen in terms of a set number like 160, but I fixed a mistake that I did the last time - add the stats rather than find their product. Normalize the stats to a scale based on the weight of the stat, and add them.</p></li>
<li><p>Milestone values : This number is suggestive of the batsman&rsquo;s ability to put up big scores. I used MongoDB aggregation to get a list of individual innings scores for each batsman. From this list, assign incremental scores to milestone innings (50-74, 75-89, 90-99, 100-124, etc.). Assign a 5-point score for the ratio of 50+ innings and total innings, and a 10+ score for the ratio of 100+ innings and 50+ innings. The sum of all these values gives the overall milestone value of the batsman.</p></li>
<li><p>Estimated Runs Added (ERA): This number feels so Sabermetrics-like. It gives how much the batsman scores more than the average runs scored at that rate. For a given batsman&rsquo;s average and strike rate, find the number of balls he would take to score that average. Also, find the runs scored for the same number of balls on the overall dataset average strike rate. The difference between the two gives a batsman&rsquo;s ERA.
ERA = Avg– ((100 * Avg / SR) * (Total runs in dataset/Total balls in dataset))</p></li>
<li><p>Over group analysis: I got this idea from an article on Cricinfo. The basic idea behind this is that a bowler&rsquo;s performance in different sections of the innings should be weighted differently. For example, a good economy rate in the death overs should be weighted more than a good economy rate in the middle overs. A team&rsquo;s innings is broken into 3 parts – the powerplay overs (overs 1-15), the middle overs (overs 16-40) and the death overs (overs 41-50). Using MongoDB aggregation, built collections with lists of runs conceded on each ball, and number of wickets taken in each section. For the runs conceded section, the total runs conceded (batsman runs + extras) is considered, thus redefining it as runs conceded to the team. For each bowler who has bowled a certain number of balls in each section, positive or negative scores were allotted for different stats compared to the overall average – dots/over, boundaries/over, economy rate, wickets/over. Weights were given depending on the over section. For example, more weight is given to dots/over in the death than in the middle overs. This basically considers that it is harder to bowl in the death than in any other point of the innings.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>With this improved set of stats, I was hopeful of better results in terms of the team I got.</p>

<p>Analysis on the teams in the next post. The final post of the series.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-tnt-journey-part-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-31T00:32:23+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/31/the-tnt-journey-part-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With all the work looking at the player side of stuff, I didn&rsquo;t spend too much time on the venue-based side of the problem. So I decided to get that done. What can sides expect in Australia and New Zealand ?</p>

<p><a href="http://plot.ly">Plotly</a> continues to impress with its usefulness.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I couldn&rsquo;t come up with any really useful statistical measure to judge the performance in a particular venue, so I decided to go with three basic numbers - runs per 50 overs, wickets per 50 overs and boundaries per 50 overs - and put them in a 3D scatter plot (which turned out to be pretty easy with Plotly).</p>

<p>It was back to MongoDB&rsquo;s aggregation framework to put this together. I went with the same workflow that I had with aggregating player data - write the aggregation commands, use a Python script to create a new collection with all the data.</p>

<p>There were 89 unique venues in the given dataset. However, we couldn&rsquo;t go with the entire set because 30 of those venues hosted only one match, and one match is definitely not enough to observe a pattern. For example, there was only one match played at the Chinnaswamy Stadium and batsmen went all berzerk during that match - that also included Rohit Sharma&rsquo;s 209. But not all matches at the Chinnaswamy produce 600+ run spectacles. So there should be a minimum number of matches that a venue should have hosted if it has to be considered. Going with a minimum of 3 matches, we have a list of 40 venues (which notably exclude MAC, Wankhede and Eden Gardens).</p>

<p>Working with these 40 venues, we set up a collection which contains the three stats that we are considering for each venue. Now it&rsquo;s just a matter of setting up the 3D scatter plot on Plotly. Since we are grouping by country, we need the country that the venue is located in. This was the annoyingly hard part - manually finding the country.</p>

<p>Now with some basic statistics on the data I have, and the generated 3D scatter plots, we can make some conclusions.</p>

<p>The scatter plot with all the countries which have venues in the dataset.</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/10.embed" width="800" height="800"></iframe>


<p>Specifically with Australia and New Zealand.</p>

<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/11.embed" width="800" height="800"></iframe>


<p>Across the 9 venues in Australia and New Zealand, the mean 50 over score increases by more than 10 to reach a score of 247, while the mean wickets/50overs remains almost the same - around 7.5. So expect many lower-order pinch hitters to make cameos. With 300+ scores becoming commonplace in ODI cricket, expect this mean 50 over score to increase over the course of the World Cup. Expect the average of 25 boundaries/50overs only from mediocre teams - if a team really has to make a mark, they&rsquo;ll have to step up that number. This World Cup is a funny mix because Australia is known for its longer boundaries, while New Zealand is known for its shorter boundaries. Batting fests are extremely possible in NZ, while Australia will host more balanced battles.</p>

<p>More insights soon.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll also continue working on finding a good way to build the team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/29/the-tnt-journey-part-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T09:17:35+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/29/the-tnt-journey-part-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you have exams and an interesting problem that you have to complete in a few days, it&rsquo;s not too cool to go down with a fever. These next couple of days are going to be a blaze with all the work. I need to get this done with.</p>

<p>Before picking the teams, I needed a way to visually represent the data I had so far. I needed to have the graphs look beautiful, and also easy to generate.</p>

<p>Enter <a href="https://plot.ly">Plotly</a></p>

<!--more-->


<p>I think of it more as, the GitHub of Graphs.</p>

<p>I heard about Plotly during PyCon India 2014. I found it really interesting and decided to use it for any interesting project I had to work on (also because I put a Plotly sticker on my laptop, so I had to use it because I donated laptop real estate to it). Just as I was looking for ideas of things to work on, I came across TNT, so I decided that it might be a good time to start using Plotly.</p>

<p>It was so much easier than I thought.</p>

<p>I decided to use the <a href="https://plot.ly/python">Plotly Python API</a> for generating some visual representations of the data. The documentation is very extensive, and the examples given are usually more than enough to get you going. The best part is how easy it is to collaborate and work on the graphs across languages/tools - when you have the link to your graph, all you have to do is add a .py or .r or .js or .m to work with the graph in Python, R, Javascript or Matlab. The link with .png gives the graph as an image, and .html gives an iframe that embeds the graph in a web page. How cool is that !</p>

<p>I decided to go with using iframes mainly because I wouldn&rsquo;t have to edit the webpage every time I edited the graph. It would be really useful when I worked on my data often.</p>

<p>So I went ahead and built histograms for each of the 7 batting/bowling statistics that I mentioned in the <a href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3/">previous post</a>.</p>

<p>Starting off with the batting stats.</p>

<ul>
<li>Runs per wicket</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/1.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Runs per 100 balls</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/2.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Pinch hitting rate</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/3.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<p>The bowling stats.</p>

<ul>
<li>Overs to concede 100 runs</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/4.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Wickets per 10 overs</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/5.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Overs to concede 10 boundaries</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/6.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<ul>
<li>Overs to concede an extra</li>
</ul>


<iframe frameborder="0" seamless="seamless" scrolling="no" src="https://plot.ly/~AlexMathew/7.embed" width="600" height="400"></iframe>


<p>Now, this is useful to notice how I can&rsquo;t use the entire player dataset to generate my team, because it would end up skewed in favour of players who rarely played. A player who has bowled only one over in the given timeframe, and conceded just 1 run along with taking a wicket will have statistics like 100 overs to concede 100 runs and 10 wickets per 10 overs - which is obviously messed up. So I need to set a minimum number of innings that a player should have batted or bowled in, if the player has to be considered for the team. I&rsquo;m setting that number at 23 - I&rsquo;ll see how it turns out and make changes if I have to.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll continue using Plotly to represent other statistics of the generated team. And that is what I&rsquo;ll have to start working on now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basketball Season Has Returned !]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/27/basketball-season-has-returned/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-27T01:04:34+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/27/basketball-season-has-returned</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The countdown to the NBA season is heating up ! The preseason is done and we&rsquo;re in the final few days before the start of the regular season. I&rsquo;ll be honest - I&rsquo;ve not been a huge fan for long. The 2013-14 season was the first one that I followed closely, and that was because I wanted to know the best teams to ask for transfers to in NBA2K14 MyCareer. But I was smitten by the NBA bug, and I was following developments in the season.</p>

<p>Now that it&rsquo;s just a few days before the start of the 2014-15 season, I thought I&rsquo;d take a shot at reviewing the rosters of all the teams, and give my opinion of how I&rsquo;d expect them to perform.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>(And it&rsquo;s almost 2 weeks into the season by the time I finished this post. So I went ahead and also reviewed the teams&#8217; start to the season.)</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll go conference and then division-wise. Starting off.</p>

<p>THE WESTERN CONFERENCE.</p>

<p>PACIFIC DIVISION.</p>

<ul>
<li>LOS ANGELES CLIPPERS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://hoops-nation.com/wp-content/uploads/Paul-Griffin-Jordan.jpg" width="350" height="350">
LOB CITY FTW ! \m/ (Sorry if I seem biased here) The onus will be on these three guys. If you ask me, the Clippers&#8217; performance will be directly dependent on the output they get out of Chris Paul, Blake Griffin and DeAndre Jordan. The effect of having Doc Rivers already showed last season, with improved defence and Griffin improving as a shooter. If CP3 stays healthy throughout the season, the Clippers are sure playoff contenders. <a href="http://www.sbnation.com/2014/10/8/6946249/blake-griffin-jumper-clippers-breakdown">Griffin looked threatening as a shooter during the preseason</a> and that should make things very interesting. The wild cards here though will be Jamal Crawford and Spencer Hawes. Crawford has been a consistent contributor off the bench, and if that continues, it will be raining heavily from deep. Hawes is a brilliant off-season signing for the Clippers, and he has turned out to be a very efficient rotation player for DJ. My heart wants them to win the title, but my mind says they will be conference semifinalists, or finalists, if things go very well.</p>

<ul>
<li>LOS ANGELES LAKERS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://standingosports.com/main/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/kobebryant11.jpg" width="350" height="350">
Oh, Lakers. Things have been bittersweet for them. Kobe returned, Nash went down again. [UPDATE: Julius Randle too. The rookie must be heartbroken. Definitely not the debut he pictured.] But I think the team can move past at it and focus on the season ahead. The effectiveness of the Boozer-Gasol trade will be on display. The wild card for the Lakers will be Jeremy Lin off the bench. If Linsanity strikes LA, it&rsquo;ll be huge for the Lakers. Will they reach the playoffs ? Depends on if Kobe lives up to the hype of his return.</p>

<ul>
<li>GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://i2.cdn.turner.com/nba/nba/dam/assets/130425225210-stephen-curry-klay-thompson-iso.mobile-t1.jpg" width="350" height="350">
It&rsquo;s their time ! I really do believe that. The Splash bros can really take this season by storm. Stephen Curry and Klay Thompson at their peaks are unstoppable. If they hit their peaks, this will turn out to be a very, very interesting season. Iggy/Barnes-Lee-Bogut in the frontcourt adds a lot of fire power to the already explosive team. Expect them to go deep into the playoffs. Also, it&rsquo;s very interesting to see this budding Clippers-Warriors rivalry.</p>

<ul>
<li>PHOENIX SUNS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://img.bleacherreport.net/img/images/photos/002/834/508/2fa0b16c66eca7933cf95c1fb3e28186_crop_north.jpg?w=630&h=420&q=75" width="350" height="350">
Expect some entertainment here, with Gerald Green. Some fun dunks ahead. Eric Bledsoe holds the key to their performance. In my opinion, he&rsquo;ll have to be the one carrying a major part of the load. It&rsquo;ll be fun to see two pairs of brothers in action here - the Dragic brothers and the Morris twins. Goran and Zoran Dragic had a good FIBA World Cup - the Suns would love for them to carry that on here.</p>

<ul>
<li>SACRAMENTO KINGS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://www.rantsports.com/clubhouse/files/2014/07/Sim-Bhullar-India-NBA-Sacramento-Kings-e1405038740695.jpg" width="350" height="350">
Don&rsquo;t expect much here. This team doesn&rsquo;t look like much of a playoff contender. Looks more like a team that&rsquo;ll be struggling to not be at the bottom of the conference. [UPDATE: And now I&rsquo;m laughing, because after I said that, they beat the Clippers.] Personally, the only reason to follow this team will be to see if they give Sim Bhullar a game. Also, I&rsquo;ll miss Darren Collison. The Clippers comeback against OKC in the Conf SFG4 will be remembered.</p>

<p>SOUTHWEST DIVISION.</p>

<ul>
<li>SAN ANTONIO SPURS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://a.espncdn.com/photo/2014/0615/nba_u_leonard11_600x400.jpg" width="350" height="350">
THE CHAMPS ! I don&rsquo;t think this is the kind of team that&rsquo;ll succumb under the pressure of trying to defend the title. They can really hold their own during the regular season, and have a great playoff run. With the Big Three of Parker-Ginobili-Duncan still performing at a high level, the focus will be on their newfound game changer - Kawhi Leonard. Once he returns from injury, he&rsquo;ll have a lot to prove this season - proving that his MVP-performance at the Finals was no fluke.</p>

<ul>
<li>HOUSTON ROCKETS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://cdn.fansided.com/wp-content/blogs.dir/307/files/2014/01/7945348.jpg" width="350" height="350">
Hopes were high last season, but they ran into <a href="http://allball.blogs.nba.com/2014/05/03/horry-scale-damian-does-it/">Damian Lillard breaking the Horry Scale</a>. The focus remains the same this season - James Harden and Dwight Howard do the majority of the heavy lifting. Howard is a beast on the boards - being a double-double machine always makes the player a huge asset for the team. What I&rsquo;ll be really interested to see is if losing Chandler Parsons hurts the Rockets. But nonetheless, a playoff berth seems pretty certain.</p>

<ul>
<li>DALLAS MAVERICKS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://www.dallasnews.com/incoming/20130408-20130330_gav_aj6_122_30403265.jpg.ece/BINARY/w620x413/20130330_GAV_AJ6_122_30403265.JPG" width="350" height="350">
The Mavs are all about the class of Dirk Nowitzki. Monta Ellis has had a lot of hype surrounding him since he joined the Mavs - he&rsquo;ll have to step up the performances if he has to make a real impact on the team. Kick up that 19.0 PPG average, and Ellis will be the difference maker. Getting Chandler Parsons is huge for them. He&rsquo;s coming off a good season where he played a major role for the Rockets - the Mavs will really look for him to continue that.</p>

<ul>
<li>MEMPHIS GRIZZLIES</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://standingosports.com/main/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wendigo111712.jpg" width="350" height="350">
Marc Gasol is going to be the focus of this team. Mike Conley and Zach Randolph in support. I don&rsquo;t know what to expect here. If the Grizzlies come up huge, it&rsquo;ll mix up the West a lot more. I think I&rsquo;ll just sit back and look forward to some Vince Carter moments.</p>

<ul>
<li>NEW ORLEANS PELICANS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://usatftw.files.wordpress.com/2013/10/usatsi_7521355-copy.jpg?w=1000" width="350" height="350">
<a href="https://twitter.com/alxmth03/status/522255547425239040">I&rsquo;ve said it before</a>, and I&rsquo;ll say it again - the Brow is going to be the breakout star this season. Anthony Davis is going to make a huge mark this season. He&rsquo;s had a great run of late, especially with Team USA. He made the most of his increased minutes last season, putting up double-doubles at will. If his form continues throughout this season, I&rsquo;d say that the Pelicans are in for a great season. Also, MJ was #23, LeBron is #23 and Davis is #23 - are we seeing a trend ?</p>

<p>NORTHWEST DIVISION.</p>

<ul>
<li>OKLAHOMA CITY THUNDER</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://img.bleacherreport.net/img/article/media_slots/photos/001/245/686/hi-res-454036275-kevin-durant-and-russell-westbrook-of-the-oklahoma-city_crop_north.jpg?w=650&h=975&q=85" width="300" height="300">
<a href="https://twitter.com/alxmth03/status/530967350476935168">They are in a bad, bad state</a>. With Durant and Westbrook out, this team looks ridiculously depleted. Serge Ibaka will have to be the man carrying this team till they return. But what&rsquo;s really exciting here is the output they can get from the younger players till then - Andre Roberson, Perry Jones and Steven Adams. Adams was pretty impressive during the last postseason, and I think it&rsquo;ll do him wonders if he carries that forward.</p>

<ul>
<li>MINNESOTA TIMBERWOLVES</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://mng-twincities.smugmug.com/New-Timberwolves-introduced-at/i-r3Nq7Lq/0/L/005%20wolves%208-26-L.jpg" width="350" height="350">
Personally, I think this is one extremely exciting team, with all the young players in the mix. I mean, the fact that 4th-year Ricky Rubio is one of the team&rsquo;s most experienced players proves how young this team is. With Andrew Wiggins, Zach LaVine and Anthony Bennett joining Rubio, the Wolves have a great framework for building a grand team for the future. As the experienced campaigners, there will be pressure on Kevin Martin, Corey Brewer and Thad Young to lead this team. I think if this young team can make it to the playoffs, it&rsquo;ll be a huge boost for them, and will help the Wolves establish themselves as a force in the league.</p>

<ul>
<li>PORTLAND TRAILBLAZERS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://footbasket.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/damian-lillard-may-2014.jpg" width="350" height="350">
After what was quite possibly the best moment in Rip City history, they bumped into a Spurs team that didn&rsquo;t look like it was going to stop. But they had a brilliant season, nonetheless, and it was primarily because of this guy. Damian Lillard had an unbelievable season last year. To prove it, look at his All Star weekend - Rising Stars Challenge, Skill Challenge, Three-pointer Contest, Dunk Contest and the All-Star Game. 5 events over a weekend. You don&rsquo;t end up with something like that unless you really killed it over the entire season. Lillard had an amazing season, and I think if he carries that forward, the Blazers are in for a great season and possibly, postseason too.</p>

<ul>
<li>DENVER NUGGETS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left" src="http://i.cdn.turner.com/nba/nba/dam/assets/121125234738-kenneth-faried-112512-dunk.1200x672.jpg" width="350" height="350">
The difference maker. The Manimal is going to have to lead this team forward. Kenneth Faried and Ty Lawson will be the ones leading the charge for the Nuggets. But I don&rsquo;t think this is a playoff team. I may be horribly wrong, but I don&rsquo;t think they can make it. I&rsquo;ll be really surprised if they make it to the playoffs.</p>

<ul>
<li>UTAH JAZZ</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right" src="http://cdn.fansided.com/wp-content/blogs.dir/98/files/2014/05/gordon-hayward-nba-utah-jazz-golden-state-warriors.jpg" width="350" height="350">
I&rsquo;m putting up this part of the post right after <a href="http://allball.blogs.nba.com/2014/11/06/horry-scale-hayward-shocks-cavaliers/">this happened</a>. Gordon Hayward is fast becoming the icon player for the Jazz. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see how much of an impact he has on the team this season - will he be able to guide them into the postseason ? Also, I&rsquo;ll be really interested to see how much of an impact Dante Exum has. He had a lot of hype coming into the league. Have to wait and see if he&rsquo;ll live up to it.</p>

<p>So here&rsquo;s my prediction for the 8 teams in the playoffs from the West - Clippers, Rockets, Warriors and Spurs are sure shot playoff teams. The other spots will be a toss between Pelicans, Suns, Wolves, Grizzlies, Blazers, Mavericks and Thunder (after KD and Westbrook return). I&rsquo;ll go with Grizzlies, Pelicans, Blazers and Thunder/Wolves (depending on KD &amp; Westbrook&rsquo;s returns).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T11:27:57+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/26/the-tnt-journey-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Records, exams, assignments. The absolute worst time possible. Indian education will not improve till they get rid of this concept of maintaining a formal record book where you write unnecessary garbage. In the middle of all this, finding time to work on the TNT problem has been hard. But I&rsquo;ve been reading, trying out stuff and making some gradual progress. And of late, I&rsquo;ve approached this in a different way. Advice from a professor gave me an interesting way to go about this problem. Implementing has been hard, but the idea behind it is brilliant.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t look for individual best performers. Put the team together and see the overall rating of the team. Pick the best team, not a collection of the best players&rdquo;. I had never thought of that, really. The best players statistic-wise could all be batsmen, and I&rsquo;d end up with a batting-heavy team with a poor bowling attack. So I had to find a way to strike a balance, by considering the team as a whole. And I considered using my professor&rsquo;s advice - genetic algorithms.</p>

<p>The idea was simple. From this <a href="http://www.obitko.com/tutorials/genetic-algorithms/ga-basic-description.php">basic introductory post about GA</a>,</p>

<blockquote><p>Algorithm is started with a set of solutions (represented by chromosomes) called population. Solutions from one population are taken and used to form a new population. This is motivated by a hope, that the new population will be better than the old one. Solutions which are selected to form new solutions (offspring) are selected according to their fitness - the more suitable they are the more chances they have to reproduce.</p></blockquote>

<p>I found a bunch of research papers, where people used GAs to do this exact thing - build fantasy cricket teams. The concept seemed simple enough - pick the parameters you want to maximise on, and implement the algorithm.</p>

<p>Implementing seemed like a bitch. The NSGA-II algorithm was an extremely computation-intensive algorithm that involved many iterations, so I knew I couldn&rsquo;t write the algorithm from scratch and expect to get an optimized implementation. I had either go for Python genetic programming libraries, or find someone else&rsquo;s implementation of the algorithm. I checked out <a href="https://code.google.com/p/deap/">Deap</a> - it looked like it could effectively give me what I needed. But setting up was really hard. I couldn&rsquo;t make much progress even after hours of reading the docs. So, Deap is on hold.</p>

<p>I found <a href="https://code.google.com/p/pynsga2/">another implementation of NSGA-II</a> that used multiprocessing to improve the speed of implementation. It required the fitness to be in a separate file - I need to try it out and see how that works.</p>

<p>So for now, it&rsquo;s still an experimentation phase with the implementation of the algorithm. I took some time out to decide the parameters I&rsquo;d want to maximise the fitness on.</p>

<p>BATSMEN :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Runs per wicket : The batting average of the batsman. For good batsmen in the current cricketing world, this number hovers around 40.</p></li>
<li><p>Runs per 100 balls : The strike rate of the batsman. A strike rate of >85 is generally considered very good. A batsman with a 100+ strike rate is an ideal pinch hitter to finish the innings.</p></li>
<li><p>Pinch hitting rate : Boundaries scored per 100 balls, with more weight given to sixes. So effectively,</p></li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="n">pinch_hitting</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mf">100.0</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fours</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mf">1.5</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">sixes</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">balls_faced</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>BOWLERS :</p>

<p>The standard bowling statistics require to be minimized on. So for convenience sake, I took the inverse of these numbers, so I could maximise on them.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Overs to concede 100 runs : A number built from the inverse of the economy rate. For good bowlers, this number is somewhere in the mid-20s.</p></li>
<li><p>Wickets per 10 overs : Built from the inverse of the bowling average. It is usually >1.5 for good strike bowlers.</p></li>
<li><p>Overs to concede 10 boundaries : Built from the inverse of the bowler&rsquo;s pinch hitting conceding rate, with weightage for sixes.</p></li>
<li><p>Overs to concede an extra : The inverse of extras per over.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The hard part is finding ways to measure fielding/wicketkeeping performance. It was possible to find the total number of field dismissals that a player, but there&rsquo;s no way to know how many matches the player played. I only have the number of innings he batted or bowled in. It is possible that he played a match where he didn&rsquo;t bat, didn&rsquo;t bowl and didn&rsquo;t have a catch or run out credited to him.</p>

<p>I need a way to quantify a player&rsquo;s field performance. And I need to see how to implement NSGA-II to draft my team.</p>

<p>Updates soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/17/the-tnt-journey-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T00:02:10+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/17/the-tnt-journey-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Step 1 : Get cummulative statistics. <a href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-tnt-journey-part-1/">Done</a>.</p>

<p>Now I need to find a way to measure the performance of these players during this period. Several people have written about different statistics to do this. I need to pick the best ones for the problem I have at hand.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Aggregation worked beautifully. I got the cummulative stats I needed to work with. Now I have to put this into a new collection and I&rsquo;m all set to go. Except, it wasn&rsquo;t that easy. Updating a collection with results from the aggregation pipeline is pretty hard. Looping through the results is too inefficient. After some research (read, StackOverflow), I found the $out pipeline stage. Seemed like just what I needed. I gave it a shot and got this.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>"errmsg" : "exception: Unrecognized pipeline stage name: '$out'"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Roadblock ! Turns out $out is a new addition in MongoDB 2.6 and I was working with 2.4. So before any more progress could happen, an update had to happen.</p>

<p>While I waited for the 100+ MB file download to complete (I have bad internet - 100MB is a big deal), I read some Quora answers and research papers on performance measures. Now I had to pick the ones that gave the most efficient results.</p>

<p>I needed some proper measures to judge how useful a player is on a team. It&rsquo;s cricket, so a player can contribute to a team in many different ways. He could be a batsman who plays the bulk of the innings to set up the score, or he could be a batsman who faces around 15 or 20 balls to make a quickfire 30. He could be the strike bowler who takes 2 or 3 wickets in his qouta of 10 overs, or he could be the bowler who restricts the opponents&#8217; run flow by conceding only at around 3 runs an over.</p>

<p>So what statistics would I have to consider ?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Batting average : Runs scored per out. Undoubtedly, one of the most argued about statistics in cricket. And for valid reasons. The batting average ends up extremely skewed in favour of players who come lower down the order, because of the higher probability that they&rsquo;d remain not out.</p></li>
<li><p>Strike rate : Runs scored per 100 balls. I remember watching cricket at a time when a strike rate of around 80 was the trademark of a &ldquo;blazing innings&rdquo;. Times have definitely changed. Higher strike rates are a major focus in batting line ups.</p></li>
<li><p>Batting pinch hitting rate : A very good idea I got out of <a href="http://www.quora.com/What-new-statistical-measures-could-make-cricket-better-in-terms-of-player-evaluation-and-viewer-experience/answer/Thomas-Foster">this Quora answer</a>. Boundaries have a huge impact on the flow of a match. It switches momentum, leads to the fielding setup getting shuffled, and so much more. This can be improved a little by giving a higher weightage to sixes (because sixes are awesome !).</p></li>
<li><p>Bowling average : Runs conceded per wicket taken. The lower, the better. Pretty efficient stat to work with.</p></li>
<li><p>Bowling strike rate : Balls bowled per wicket. Because strike bowlers strike often.</p></li>
<li><p>Bowling pinch hitting rate : If it can be used to quantify a batsman&rsquo;s performance, it can be used for bowlers too. Batsmen want to score boundaries, bowlers should make sure they can&rsquo;t.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I need to find a way to work with all of these numbers together. And there should be an efficient way to strike a balance. Hashim Amla may not be the quickest scorer, but he definitely scores a lot. James Anderson has an average economy rate, but he&rsquo;s one of the best strike bowlers in the world. Normalize, combine these stats into one index - I need to see what works best.</p>

<p>In other MongoDB news, it turns out $out is not what I need. I need to combine the results from multiple aggregation commands into one collection, but $out puts the result from one aggregation command into one collection. So I need to move back to my original option of looping through the results. Fire IPython, <code>import pymongo</code> and get to work.</p>

<p>Now that I have player-wise statistics, I need to find the most efficient way to quantify their overall performance and pick the best performers.</p>

<p>Part 3 may take a while to come out. I&rsquo;ll work on some options and make one grand update on my progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The TNT Journey - Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-tnt-journey-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T14:58:04+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-tnt-journey-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>And so, the journey with TNT begins. A 175K+ row dataset. A new challenge.</p>

<p>Over the next few posts, I&rsquo;ll document the various facets of my approach to this problem. Part 1 - how do I get started ?</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I registered for the event a few days after I heard about it. I thought I&rsquo;d give myself time to get some basic idea in place before I get started. So I took my time to read about various statistics that people proposed and how it&rsquo;d help in finding the most efficient players. In my head, it felt like Brad Pitt and Jonah Hill discussing Sabermetrics. I loved how people were crunching numbers to produce evidence of how the statistic they proposed was effective. It seemed simple enough - work with their averages and strike rates and other basic statistics. With the expected basic idea in place, I registered for TNT, and later that day, I got the link to the dataset. Downloaded the file, unzipped it and opened the Excel sheet. And then the bomb dropped.</p>

<p>Ball-by-ball data.</p>

<p>Somehow, I didn&rsquo;t expect that I would have to work with ball-by-ball data. In its native form, ball-by-ball stats are pretty useless (unless you&rsquo;re analyzing run rate patterns and everything). So before getting to work with various performance measures, I had to put the available data together into cummulative stats.</p>

<p>I had a CSV file to work with. I had to pick my weapon to get started. I had a few options.</p>

<p>Option 1 - R. I&rsquo;d always wanted to get started with learning R. I never found a compelling reason to get around to working with it. This seemed like a very good starting point. But I didn&rsquo;t want to learn something from scratch for this. I thought it&rsquo;d be a low-efficiency move to tread into unfamiliar territory, just to work with this dataset. So R, maybe later. Ruled out for now.</p>

<p>Option 2 - Pandas. Familiarity with Python, check. An interest to work with the data side of Python, check. But Pandas is very vast. Getting a base with NumPy to just get started is very hard. So SciPy stack, sometime soon, but not now. Ruled out for now.</p>

<p>I had a large dataset that I had to break into cummulative stats of each player. And I needed somewhere to store it. I would use a database anyway, so why not use it to also aggregate the data the way I need it ? And that was option 3.</p>

<p>Option 3 - MongoDB. I had done some basic work with MongoDB. The M101P course (which, even after 3 attempts, I haven&rsquo;t been able to finish) gave me a decent base with the CRUD and aggregation operations. 175K row dataset - bring out the aggregation framework !</p>

<p>Importing the data into a DB was easier than I thought.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ mongoimport --db tnt --collection odi --type csv --file ODI.csv --headerline </span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And that was done. Easy stuff.</p>

<p>The hard part was writing aggregation commands to do the required grouping. It&rsquo;s sort of like writing regular expressions - extremely hard, very annoying, but so damn powerful. After a lot of reference from the MongoDB docs and StackOverflow, I managed to get the stats I needed. For example, to get the total runs that a batsman scored.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>MongoDB aggregation to find total runs scored</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="nx">db</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">odi</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">aggregate</span><span class="p">([{</span> <span class="nx">$group</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nx">_id</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$Batsman&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">Runs</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nx">$sum</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;$Runs Batsman&quot;</span> <span class="p">}</span> <span class="p">}</span> <span class="p">},</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="nx">$sort</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="p">{</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Runs&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span> <span class="p">}</span> <span class="p">}])</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p></p>

<p>Some easy ones and some hard. And I managed to get the stats I needed.</p>

<p>Now, step 2. I need to put this together and build some performance measures.</p>

<p>Part 2 of this series will be up when I have some significant progress on that front.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cause I'm TNT, I'm Dynamite]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/cause-im-tnt/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T23:33:31+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/cause-im-tnt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(Yes, I just made an AC/DC reference)</p>

<p>First off, huge shout out to LatentView Analytics. Thank you for the job placement offer ! It&rsquo;s given me so much peace of mind, and in turn, freedom to experiment with new stuff.</p>

<p>About a week back, I heard about LatentView&rsquo;s new event for final and pre-final years - &ldquo;The Number Thing&rdquo;. Or, TNT. Perfect experimentation ground.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>All the problems were interesting. It was just a matter of picking the right one.</p>

<p>Cricket stat analysis.
Crime pattern analysis.
Text analysis.</p>

<p>One sports analytics question, and I was sold. That was my choice. Cricket Craze.</p>

<p>I knew it would be a lot of fun. I also expected it to be challenging. What I didn&rsquo;t expect was a 175373-row dataset. I knew this would be a whole new challenge for me. This was the biggest dataset I&rsquo;ve had to work with so far. I had to get new tools in my arsenal to tackle this. This was going to be a crazy ride.</p>

<p>I decided to blog about what my approach to this problem. Think of it as documentation. Over the next few posts, I&rsquo;ll break down my approach - from the initial steps, all the way down to the final result (hopefully!).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this and think there&rsquo;s a better way than the approach I&rsquo;ve taken, do give your suggestions ! Also, suggest resources to get started with them. You can write to me at alexmathew003[at]gmail[dot]com</p>

<p>Check out the &ldquo;TNT&rdquo; category on the blog to read the posts. I&rsquo;ll make regular updates as I make progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Beginnings]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/the-beginnings/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T23:07:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrasis.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/15/the-beginnings</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the beginning, there was nothing. And then I said &ldquo;Let there be a blog&rdquo;. And it was done.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I&rsquo;ve always wanted to do this. Laziness always stopped me. But I&rsquo;m not going to let it stop me anymore. I&rsquo;ve made the decision now. I am going to maintain this blog.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have any particular agenda of what I&rsquo;m going to put in here. Just my thoughts/opinions/reviews of stuff, a live blog of anything I&rsquo;m working on. Just to give some direction to my ideas. I&rsquo;m not going to try to make this huge and viral. I&rsquo;ll just let this lie in a corner of the vast expanse of the Internet, so I can look at it some day and recollect how I went about stuff (or say &ldquo;what was I thinking ?&rdquo;).</p>

<p>Let the ride begin. And may the blog be forever in your favour.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
