<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nba | Periphrastic Prolixity]]></title>
  <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/categories/nba/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-27T12:08:31+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alex Mathew]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alexmathew003@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basketball Season Has Returned !]]></title>
    <link href="http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/27/basketball-season-has-returned/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-27T01:04:34+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://periphrastic-prolixity.herokuapp.com/blog/2014/10/27/basketball-season-has-returned</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The countdown to the NBA season is heating up ! The preseason is done and we&rsquo;re in the final few days before the start of the regular season. I&rsquo;ll be honest - I&rsquo;ve not been a huge fan for long. The 2013-14 season was the first one that I followed closely, and that was because I wanted to know the best teams to ask for transfers to in NBA2K14 MyCareer. But I was smitten by the NBA bug, and I was following developments in the season.</p>

<p>Now that it&rsquo;s just a few days before the start of the 2014-15 season, I thought I&rsquo;d take a shot at reviewing the rosters of all the teams, and give my opinion of how I&rsquo;d expect them to perform.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;ll go conference and then division-wise. Starting off.</p>

<p>THE WESTERN CONFERENCE.</p>

<p>PACIFIC DIVISION.</p>

<ul>
<li>LOS ANGELES CLIPPERS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://hoops-nation.com/wp-content/uploads/Paul-Griffin-Jordan.jpg">http://hoops-nation.com/wp-content/uploads/Paul-Griffin-Jordan.jpg</a>&#8221; width=&#8221;350&#8221; height=&#8221;350&#8221;>
LOB CITY FTW ! \m/ (Sorry if I seem biased here) The onus will be on these three guys. If you ask me, the Clippers&#8217; performance will be directly dependent on the output they get out of Chris Paul, Blake Griffin and DeAndre Jordan. The effect of having Doc Rivers already showed last season, with improved defence and Griffin improving as a shooter. If CP3 stays healthy throughout the season, the Clippers are sure playoff contenders. <a href="http://www.sbnation.com/2014/10/8/6946249/blake-griffin-jumper-clippers-breakdown">Griffin looked threatening as a shooter during the preseason</a> and that should make things very things. The wild cards here though will be Jamal Crawford and Spencer Hawes. Crawford has been a consistent contributor off the bench, and if that continues, it will be raining heavily from deep. Hawes is a brilliant off-season signing for the Clippers, and he has turned out to be a very efficient rotation player for DJ. My heart wants them to win the title, but my mind says they will be conference semifinalists, or finalists, if things go very well.</p>

<ul>
<li>LOS ANGELES LAKERS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left <a" src="href="http://standingosports.com/main/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/kobebryant11.jpg">http://standingosports.com/main/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/kobebryant11.jpg</a>&#8221; width=&#8221;350&#8221; height=&#8221;350&#8221;>
Oh, Lakers. Things have been bittersweet for them. Kobe returned, Nash went down again. But I think the team can move past at it and focus on the season ahead. The effectiveness of the Boozer-Gasol trade will be on display. I think Boozer is more useful on the frontcourt. The wild card for the Lakers will be Jeremy Lin off the bench. If Linsanity strikes LA, it&rsquo;ll be huge for the Lakers. Will they reach the playoffs ? Depends on if Kobe lives up to the hype of his return.</p>

<ul>
<li>GOLDEN STATE WARRIORS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://i2.cdn.turner.com/nba/nba/dam/assets/130425225210-stephen-curry-klay-thompson-iso.mobile-t1.jpg">http://i2.cdn.turner.com/nba/nba/dam/assets/130425225210-stephen-curry-klay-thompson-iso.mobile-t1.jpg</a>&#8221; width=&#8221;350&#8221; height=&#8221;350&#8221;>
It&rsquo;s their time ! I really do believe that. The Splash bros can really take this season by storm. Stephen Curry and Klay Thompson at their peaks are unstoppable. If they hit their peaks, this will turn out to be a very, very interesting season. Iggy/Harrison Barnes at SF adds a lot of fire power to the already explosive team. Expect them to go deep into the playoffs.</p>

<ul>
<li>PHOENIX SUNS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="left <a" src="href="http://img.bleacherreport.net/img/images/photos/002/834/508/2fa0b16c66eca7933cf95c1fb3e28186_crop_north.jpg?w=630&amp;h=420&amp;q=75">http://img.bleacherreport.net/img/images/photos/002/834/508/2fa0b16c66eca7933cf95c1fb3e28186_crop_north.jpg?w=630&amp;h=420&amp;q=75</a>&#8221; width=&#8221;350&#8221; height=&#8221;350&#8221;>
Expect some entertainment here, with Gerald Green. Some fun dunks ahead. Eric Bledsoe holds the key to their performance. In my opinion, he&rsquo;ll have to be the one carrying a major part of the load. It&rsquo;ll be fun to see two pairs of brothers in action here - the Dragic brothers and the Morris twins. Goran and Zoran Dragic had a good FIBA World Cup - the Suns would love for them to carry that on here.</p>

<ul>
<li>SACRAMENTO KINGS</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://www.rantsports.com/clubhouse/files/2014/07/Sim-Bhullar-India-NBA-Sacramento-Kings-e1405038740695.jpg">http://www.rantsports.com/clubhouse/files/2014/07/Sim-Bhullar-India-NBA-Sacramento-Kings-e1405038740695.jpg</a>&#8221; width=&#8221;350&#8221; height=&#8221;350&#8221;>
Don&rsquo;t expect much here. This team doesn&rsquo;t look like much of a playoff contender. Looks more like a team that&rsquo;ll be struggling to not be at the bottom of the conference. Personally, the only reason to follow this team will be to see if they give Sim Bhullar a game. Also, I&rsquo;ll miss Darren Collison. The Clippers comeback against OKC in the Conf SFG4 will be remembered.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
